NARRATOR : In the 17th century , Satan was abroad on the Earth
and great was the wrath against those monstrous beings ,
thirsty for human blood ,
to whom tradition has given the name of " vampires " .
No appeal for pity or mercy availed .
Brothers did not hesitate to accuse brothers
and fathers accused sons
in the frantic attempt to purify the Earth of that horrible race
of blood-devouring assassins .
But before putting them to death ,
human justice anticipated divine judgment
by burning into the flesh of those damned ones
the brand of Satan .
Asa , daughter of the House of Vajda ,
this High Court of the Inquisition of Moldavia
has declared you guilty .
I , the second-born son of Prince Vajda ,
as Grand Inquisitor , do condemn you .
And as your brother , I repudiate you .
Too many evil deeds have you done to satisfy your monstrous love
for that serf of the Devil , lgor Javutich .
May God have pity on your soul in this , your final hour .
Cover her face with the mask of Satan .
Nail it down !
May the cleansing flames reduce her foul body to ashes
so that the wind will obliterate all trace of her existence .
No ... no !
No !
Griabby !
It is I who repudiate you ,
and in the name of Satan I place a curse upon you .
Go ahead ,
tie me down to the stake ,
but you will never escape my hunger , nor that of Satan !
The unchained elements of the powers of darkness are lying in ambush .
Beware , Griabby !
My revenge will strike down you and your accursed house ,
and in the blood of your sons and the sons of their sons
I will continue to live , immortal !
They will restore to me the life that you now rob from me .
I shall return to torment and destroy throughout the night of time .
.
NARRATOR : As if by the Demon 's command ,
the sudden fury of the elements extinguishes the purifying flames .
The terrorised people run in flight from that cursed place . '
And for all that long night , the church bells toll
to keep away the spirits of evil .
When the wrath is spent ,
the body of Javutich is covered with unconsecrated earth
in the burying place reserved for murderers .
And the body of Asa , the witch , is placed in the tomb of her ancestors .
.
Coachman ! Coachman !
How much further to the crossroads at Mirgorod ?
Six or seven versts , my lord .
Did you hear that , sir ?
If we stop at Mirgorod , we 'll never reach Moscow by evening .
It doesn 't matter . We can spend the night at the inn at Mirgorod .
Good smoked salmon and excellent vodka !
We 'll still be in time for the congress tomorrow .
But we 'll miss the opening address .
Too bad . Dr Blistanov of St Petersburg will be there , and Dr Steiner of Vienna .
How long have you had your degree ?
Three years , Professor . I 've been with you for two .
When you 've been in the profession as long as I have ,
you learn to take all the speeches at these conferences with a grain of salt .
Coachman ! Stop !
Ho !
Take the forest road , it 's shorter .
It 's full of holes . No one uses it .
I understand . You 're afraid of the witch !
It 's not so easy to frighten me ,
I fought through the war against Napoleon ,
but to tell you the truth ,
I 'd rather find myself face to face with a cursed Frenchman than ...
than meet up with a ghost .
This will help you to forget all about ghosts . Here you are !
Come on , now , let 's get going !
Ho !
What 's that wailing ?
It 's nothing , just the wind in the trees .
- What 's happened ? - The branches of the tree , sir .
That branch reached out and tried to choke me .
Try not to choke yourself with that vodka . Now , get a move on !
Ho ! Ho !
Why is he in such a hurry ?
Well , between my tip and his fear ...
Oh !
Oh , what a mess ! Dear heaven !
Dear heaven , of all places for this to happen .
- Oh ! - Is it serious ?
No , no . Fortunately it just slipped out of the socket .
I 'll have it back in no time .
- Just a minute . - Good .
It certainly isn 't very cheerful here .
That weird sound .
It 's coming from there . Let 's see what it is .
There ! You see ?
It 's just the wind in the pipes of this broken-down organ .
Agh !
What 's happening , my lords ?
It 's nothing . Continue with your work .
More than a thousand years of conflicts , hates and loves
all reduced to dust in these tombs .
Nothing remains of the ancient princes of Vajda
but the dead shadows of their former glory .
The history of ancient Moldavia is carved in these stones .
Andre , come here .
This is the witch of the old legend .
See this bronze mask ?
One was always placed over the face of a condemned witch
so she would wear for all eternity her true face , the face of Satan .
Why is there a window ?
They feared the witch might rise again
and maintained that a cross visible to her through the glass
would keep her nailed down forever .
- Incredible ! - My lords !
My lords , where are you ?
Someone had better come and help me with this wheel .
Please don 't leave me all alone in this infernal place !
He 's frightened to death .
Go and help him . I want to have another look around .
Frankly , I prefer it outside .
Not only is there no air in here , but it 's also a little gloomy .
Professor ?
Professor Kruvajan , what happened ?
- Why did you fire ? - Look here .
That monster attacked me for some reason .
That 's very strange .
Usually bats shy away from human beings .
Let 's get out of here , Professor . We 'll be better off outside .
Otherwise the coachman will be convinced that he 's right .
Wait .
What are you doing ?
Still intact after two centuries .
Oh , you 've cut yourself .
You 're right , I hadn 't noticed it .
It must have been a splinter of glass .
Just a drop or two of blood , that 's all .
Those empty eyes seem to be looking at us .
All right , we 'll go .
Who are you ?
What do you want ?
I am Professor Choma Kruvajan and this is my assistant .
Andre Gorobec .
I was walking in the park when I heard a shot .
What happened ?
I killed a large bat down in the crypt .
You must excuse us for taking the liberty of entering the chapel ,
but we thought it was an abandoned ruin .
We wanted to satisfy our curiosity .
It 's all so strange , so mysterious here .
Everything is going to ruin .
My father , Prince Vajda , refuses to repair even this old chapel .
This place , in his eyes , is a curse .
My lords , the wheel is repaired . We can go now .
All right , we 're coming .
Please excuse us , Princess , but we must go .
We still have five versts to go to Mirgorod .
We are spending the night there .
If you don 't mind , I won 't say goodbye to you .
Perhaps we will meet again .
Yes ...
I trust you will spend a good night at ... Mirgorod .
Well , spellbound ?
What sadness in her eyes .
But look ...
Ah , a souvenir of the witch .
Like a voice breaking off .
- What 's that ? - Wolves !
That 's why I couldn 't find any tracks of wild deer today in the forest .
No , it seems to be something else out there .
Those are not wolves .
The griffin moved .
Constantine ! Katia !
- What is it ? - Father !
- It wasn 't painted like that . - What ?
It was alive before . Now it 's dead .
- What are you saying ? - I 'm certain .
Father 's right , it wasn 't in that position before .
Katia , that portrait has always had a strange effect on you . I wonder why .
It 's like a flame that can 't escape .
There 's something alive about it ,
something different about the eyes , the hands ,
as if it were hiding something .
Sometimes I 'm afraid to go near it .
Katia !
Maybe Constantine is right .
I must have been dreaming .
We 'll say no more about it .
How cold it is !
A chill seems to come out of the fireplace tonight that penetrates into my bones .
Why don 't you get some sleep , Father ? Your eyes are tired .
No , my eyes aren 't tired .
My spirit is .
You two go to bed now . I want to be alone .
Good night .
- Good night , my lord . - No , wait , Ivan .
You 've served in this house for many years .
I was born here , sir .
Today 's the feast of St George .
You must know the legend of the curse that was placed on this castle .
Two centuries ago today , two people were executed for practising witchcraft .
Princess Asa and her accomplice , Prince Javutich .
And to their faces was nailed the mask of Satan .
A hundred years later , again on St George 's Day ,
an earthquake destroyed only the ancient chapel ,
and the witch 's tomb was found split open ,
as if Asa had tried to break out to accomplish her revenge .
In fact , that same night Princess Macha died mysteriously .
Macha was beautiful , the very image of Asa .
She was just 21 that day .
Like Katia .
And Katia is her living image .
It 's as if the witch tormented her victims with her own beauty before killing them .
And it 's this resemblance , this repeating of Asa 's vengeance that terrorises me .
I 'm afraid , Ivan .
You mustn 't be afraid , my lord .
The cross will protect you .
Even if what you said is true ,
these monsters are terrified by the sacred symbol of Christ .
Always have it near you and you 'll be safe .
Yes , you 're right , Ivan .
It 's the atmosphere surrounding this cursed day that has upset me so .
Drink your toddy , sir , before it gets cold .
It 's death ! I 've just seen death !
It 's a warning , Ivan . I won 't be afraid .
They won 't win . They cannot win against the symbol of Christ .
- Everything all right , sir ? - Yes , thank you .
You were right , Professor , this vodka is great .
Right now I feel as if I could conquer the world .
Starting with the castle .
If I 'm not mistaken , someone there made quite an impression on you .
An excellent idea ! Another little drink or two
and that 's exactly where I 'd go .
You 'd be wiser to go to sleep .
Mysterious princesses are more easily conquered in dreams .
Besides , we must be up early tomorrow .
You 're right .
- Er ... I 'll tell them to call us at five . - No , no , don 't bother , I 'll do it .
I 'll take a little walk and then tell the innkeeper .
- All right . Good night . - Good night .
And watch out for bats !
Watch out for your head !
No !
No , no .
- Why do you always carry on like this ? - I don 't want to go .
Who do you think should go ? Me , with all I have to do ?
Oh , excuse me , sir , but isn 't it shameful that a big girl like her
is afraid to go to milk the cow in the barn ?
Your mother is right .
She didn 't say that the barn is beside the old haunted cemetery .
You mustn 't be afraid of the dead . They sleep soundly .
Hear what the gentleman said ? I 'm coming !
Hurry . I 'm busy . Get a move on !
- I 've been waiting for a half-hour . - I 'll go tonight , but tomorrow I won 't .
Ohh !
Hello , Irina .
Rise , Javutich !
Javutich !
Rise !
Be still , Irina . Be still .
Are you frightened , too ?
Oh , it 's a storm .
Be good , Irina .
No !
Father !
- No ! No ! - Father !
Look at me , Father . It 's Katia . Look at me !
- We must find a doctor . - But where ?
At the inn .
I met two doctors today in front of the chapel .
They said they were staying at Mirgorod .
Hurry , Ivan ! Go down and wake up the groom .
Here I am , Master . I heard someone scream .
Go to the inn and get one of the doctors . At once !
Yes , Master .
- Dr Kruvajan ! - Yes ?
Princess Vajda has sent me . Her father is very ill .
She begs you to come to the castle .
I 'll come , but first I must tell them at the inn .
You won 't need to . I 've already done so .
They told me there where I could find you .
Ah . Very well , then .
Hey !
Kruvajan !
I 've been waiting for you .
I need you again .
Look into my eyes .
Look into my eyes !
Come closer !
Just a few drops of your blood brought me to life again .
All of your blood will give me the strength to accomplish my vengeance .
Come ! Kiss me !
My lips will transform you .
You will be dead to men , but you will be alive in death .
What 's keeping Boris ? He 's been gone so long .
He 'll be back any moment now .
The griffin , the man in the painting ...
- What 's he saying ? - He 's delirious .
No , no , only the crucifix can save us
on this day of the damned .
Did you send for me ?
I 'm so grateful to you for coming . My father is delirious .
I 'll take a look at him . You may go now .
What 's wrong with him , Doctor ?
Nothing serious . He 's just had a slight shock .
We were asleep when all of a sudden we heard a frightening scream .
When we came in , he was trembling with his arm outstretched ,
holding this cross to keep back some horrible apparition .
Take it away !
He mustn 't see it . It might provoke another attack .
Our eternal sleep has been broken .
You were able to do it .
You tore me out of the earth that weighed heavily on me .
This time you are not alone .
I will bring you her body .
She will be your victim .
She was born for this fate .
She is your living image .
Destiny has its way , Asa .
In her you will live again ,
speak again
and smile as she does .
We 'll live once more , as we used to .
Get some rest , Constantine . Father is sleeping quietly .
- No , I 'm not tired . - Go , both of you . I will stay here .
Oh , dear , those dogs keep howling so !
Ivan , try to quiet them .
Yes , my lady .
You go . I 'll stay here .
- But if ... - I 'll call you if necessary .
All right , then .
What 's the matter ?
Shh ... quiet now !
What is it ?
I thought you 'd fallen asleep . Why don 't you go to bed now ?
I 'll stay and watch over your father .
But aren 't you leaving Mirgorod at dawn ?
It doesn 't matter . I can stay the night here .
He seems to be much calmer now , doesn 't he ?
Yes . You 'll see he 'll have a restful night 's sleep .
You needn 't worry any more .
Go and get some rest yourself . You must need it .
Doctor , I don 't know how to thank you .
Please call me if there should be any change .
I am sure there will be no need .
Your room is across the corridor here .
- Good night , and thank you again . - Good night .
Katia !
- Poor father ! - No !
Dr Kruvajan !
No , Katia ! Don 't go !
Katia , don 't ... Don 't look , Katia !
Professor Kruvajan !
It 's Andre .
Your friend has already left the inn .
- Left ? - Last night . He was called to the castle .
It seems that Prince Vajda was suddenly taken seriously ill .
He hasn 't come back yet .
- I wonder why he didn 't take me . - Maybe he didn 't want to disturb you .
My daughter saw him get in the coach that came from the castle to pick him up .
- Could I have a horse ? - Right away . Come with me .
Be careful ! If you upset the basket , I 'll fix you !
Say ! Excuse me .
Is this the shortest road to the Vajda castle ?
- Yes , sir , take the one going uphill . - Thank you .
The current 's stronger down here .
Oh , please ! I told you not to play around here !
- The shirt 's fallen in the water ! - There it is !
A shirt ! Oh , how am I going to catch it ?
Watch out or you 'll fall in the water , too !
There it is ! It 's getting closer . There it is !
Who is it ?
Ohh !
Dr Kruvajan !
Who are you ? What do you want ?
I am Dr Gorobec .
I heard that Dr Kruvajan was called to the castle last night .
Yes , that is correct .
We called him to attend my father , who had a sudden attack of shock .
We left the doctor alone with him , but he went away .
If he hadn 't left my father alone like this , he might still be alive .
I must say , I don 't understand your colleague 's strange behaviour in this case .
You 're right .
I don 't know how to explain it ,
but I assure you I am much more surprised than you are .
I know Professor Kruvajan very well .
I don 't understand .
Something serious must have happened , I am sure of it .
It 's very strange . When I left the inn , he still hadn 't returned .
He 's not there ?
Please , come up .
Merciful heaven , it 's Boris , the groom from the castle .
I want to see ! Let me by !
That 's who it is . Poor Boris !
He looks terrible . How did he end up here ?
The river . Can 't you see he 's dead ?
- Ah ... - Katia !
- We must take her away . - Yes .
- Where is her room ? - This way .
Quickly , some water .
The features of his face are changed .
They are not human . It 's like the face of Satan .
It made me sick to see it .
It 's as if the Demon had devoured him from the inside .
Shh . Don 't talk so loud .
Maybe it 's better not to tell them . They 're stricken by their father 's death .
Ivan ! What 's this all about ?
They 've found Boris 's body , my lord , down by the stream .
Boris 's body ?
Yes , Your Excellency . You should see how he looks .
His eyes are popping out of their sockets , his teeth are bared ,
and his hands are clenched .
Where is he now ?
We carried him into the sacristy . The parish priest is with him .
- You there ! - Me ?
Yes . Come here .
Your mother says you saw the carriage that came to fetch Dr Kruvajan .
Yes , my lord .
I saw it as I was coming back from the barn .
I heard a noise , so I hid in the bushes .
But it wasn 't Boris who was driving the coach .
I know Boris 's face very well .
It was a stranger . At least , I 've never seen him before .
- Are you sure ? - Oh , yes , my lord .
I 'm going to the village to see Boris 's body .
And you come with me , but remember , you must tell me everything you know .
Do you understand that ? It 's very important .
Certainly , sir . I 'll tell you everything .
Go on . So long , now .
Go on to your houses . Go on .
That 's the man !
Yes ! That 's who it is !
The man who came last night to get Dr Kruvajan .
I swear it , my lord . That 's the man . I 'm certain .
I could see him clearly . The moon was shining on his face .
Whose face ?
Enough of this child 's fantasies
about a portrait of someone who 's been lying dead for centuries ,
or else we 'll all go mad .
Calm yourself , Princess .
I must leave you now , but I 'll be back .
And try to be courageous .
We 'd be glad to have you stay here with us tonight , Doctor .
Yes .
Please do , we 'll feel so much safer .
It 's incredible .
He died in the same horrible way as the Prince .
The wounds on his neck look like the work of a wild beast ,
but one who punctures the flesh without tearing it .
As a doctor I have complete faith in science , but ...
And this strange behaviour of Professor Kruvajan .
It doesn 't seem possible that a man such as he could abandon a patient
and disappear without saying anything .
On my way here I passed by the inn , but no one had seen him ,
and the innkeeper 's daughter insisted today
that the man in the portrait at the castle is the same as the driver
who came last night to fetch Professor Kruvajan .
It makes my head spin . I don 't understand .
The man in the portrait , did you say ?
Yes , the portrait hanging near the fireplace .
An old 17th-century painting .
A painting of a man in black with a silver griffin embroidered on his chest ?
Yes . Why ?
Nothing . Nothing .
Oh , Father .
Prince Constantine would like you to prepare the funeral for tomorrow .
Yes , very well . Everything will be ready for tomorrow .
Go !
Help !
Help me !
What is it ? Katia ?
- What is it , Princess ? - There 's someone hiding in my room .
- Where ? - Behind the curtain .
Come ! Ivan , stand guard in the salon .
Over there , behind the curtain .
There 's nobody there . You must have imagined it .
No ! I saw it through the mirror . I saw a hand .
You don 't believe me , but I tell you , Constantine , I saw it , I saw it ...
- I 'll get her a sedative . - Katia , don 't cry .
Professor Kruvajan , it 's you ! You frightened me .
Where have you been ? What happened ?
I 've been searching for you all day .
Your hair !
Go away , Andre . Far away from here .
Don 't get involved in things that don 't concern you .
Since you didn 't come to the inn , I brought your luggage here for you .
Look , I was just trying to decipher this inscription .
Professor !
Krug ! Brug !
- They 're bleeding to death . - Yes , and I think I know who ...
Come now . Quickly !
Carry everything into the salon where the coffin will be set up .
Take this . Easy , there .
And he fled from you in terror ?
Yes , the moment I showed him the icon
he disappeared without any explanation .
It 's very difficult to find the right translation
for these old Cyrillic inscriptions .
The important thing is to get the key word .
If I take it with me , I 'll compare it with some texts I have in the library .
- I 'd be so grateful to you . - Father .
As you know , my sister 's been suffering terribly from these shocking events .
I 'd appreciate it if you could urge her to leave the castle .
I tried to convince her , but it was useless .
She said it would be disrespectful .
Princess Katia .
I hope I 'm not intruding .
No , I just feel so desperate and alone .
I understand , but you mustn 't despair .
You must always have faith in yourself , in life .
In life ?
What is my life ? Sadness and grief .
Something that destroys itself day by day , and no one can rebuild it .
Here is the very image of my life .
Look at it .
It 's being consumed hour by hour like this garden .
Abandoned to a purposeless existence .
If the hand of man abandons this castle ,
or even this Earth ,
there is no reason why you should do likewise with your life and your youth .
Go far away from here and you will be happy again , Katia .
Forgive me if I call you by name .
And remember that I 'll always be ready to help you .
You 're very kind , Andre ,
but today everything seems so hopeless .
I feel a sense of terror , a presentiment of death ,
of being destroyed by something that 's inside me .
How I wish I had your faith , your strength .
You mustn 't give in to despair .
I know it 's hard for you ,
but even here in this garden the sun will reach into the darkest corners
and chase away the shadows of the night .
Andre , help me .
I beg you to help me .
Oh !
Thank you .
Without you I wouldn 't have had the courage to go on .
In moments like this it 's difficult to ... find the right words , but ...
when this is all over , Katia ...
Thank you , Andre .
Thank you .
It was the only way I could think of to put out the fire , my lord .
Strange .
I wonder what can be hidden behind here .
Doctor !
When Ivan was putting out a fire that had started in a hanging
he ripped through this canvas .
- Look . - Be careful .
It 's pitch-black inside here .
A secret passageway .
Then my father was not delirious .
And his last words were " the silver griffin " and " the man in the portrait " .
This is where I found the dogs with their throats slashed ,
where Kruvajan disappeared .
Let 's go in .
You stay here , Ivan .
Make sure the door doesn 't close . Don 't move .
No , my lord .
It 's the same girl as the portrait in the salon .
The witch in the crypt .
How did you know about her ?
I saw her when Dr Kruvajan and I visited the abandoned chapel .
Wait a minute .
Two days ago , this tomb was intact , and the witch ...
She looks as if she had just died .
Look !
She 's breathing .
We 're in the presence of some unnatural mystery .
I must talk to the priest .
You return to the castle . Don 't leave Katia alone for a moment .
Go out that way , you 'll get to the stables quicker .
Ivan !
From what you tell me , there can be no more doubt .
We are faced by the unleashed powers of the Demon .
The ancient words on the icon explain exactly what must be done .
We must find the grave of Javutich ... before sunset .
Father !
- Yes ? - Look , the mask of Satan .
Like the one I saw over the witch 's face .
It 's just as I had feared .
We 'll find him buried here .
Look ! A freshly dug grave .
Open the coffin .
It 's Dr Kruvajan .
But ... last night ... he was still alive .
I saw him .
No , he was already dead .
But it 's impossible , Father .
He moved , even spoke to me .
Then he ran away .
Sometimes Satan , with his capacity of doing evil ,
even plays tricks with the dead .
You see ? This is the proof .
Now we must find a way for his poor soul to rest in peace .
Yes , but how ?
The inscription on the icon indicates the only way .
The spell is broken .
Poor Kruvajan .
We must take action .
And quickly , for now it is all clear .
The witch had transformed your friend into the slave of the Devil .
Dead during the day , but alive by night ,
so he could carry out Satan 's nefarious orders .
- Then the Prince , too ? - Yes .
But now we will have to make haste ,
for the witch may regain her life completely .
How could she ?
By possessing and entering the body of a young woman .
- Katia ! - Yes , Katia .
Hurry back to the castle . It 's late .
Before the sun goes down , go to the crypt and pierce the left eye of the witch .
Go now .
I will do the same to the body of Boris , which is still in the sacristy .
And then I 'll join you .
Constantine ?
Ivan ?
Where is everyone ?
Where have you gone ?
Help !
Where are you ?
Constantine !
Andre !
Help me , Father !
Please help me .
Don 't leave me alone with all these horrors .
Father !
Father ? Father !
I am no longer your father .
My blood is no longer your blood .
The spirits of evil have rent that tie between us forever ,
and an accursed poison flows in your veins .
Ohh !
No !
Constantine !
Ivan !
Open up !
At last your vengeance is at hand , Asa .
Now you will be free forever .
Katia !
Constantine !
Where are you ?
Katia ! Constantine !
Katia !
You did not know that you were born for this moment .
You didn 't know that your life had been consecrated to me by Satan ,
but you sensed it , didn 't you ?
You sensed it , didn 't you ?
That 's why my portrait was a constant temptation to you ,
why it frightened you .
You felt your life and your body were mine .
You felt like me because you were destined to become me ,
a useless body without life .
The love that young man had for you could have saved you .
You might have been happy together , but I was stronger
and now you shall enjoy a beautiful life of evil and hate in me .
No !
Constantine !
Don 't worry about me .
Save Katia .
Don 't lose time .
Save Katia ... from the witch .
Katia !
Katia , thank heaven ... that I 've arrived in time .
Yes , she wanted to kill me .
Quick , Andre , do something before it 's too late .
I couldn 't do it . Quickly .
Yes , yes , you 're right .
We must destroy her forever ,
and I know how it can be done .
Don 't look , Katia .
It 's horrible , but I must do it .
But this is your cross .
Katia ! How is it possible ?
I understand .
Come .
No !
No , I am not your love .
There she lies , dead .
Forever . Forever .
My vengeance is complete .
All of her family is destroyed . All !
Look , Andre . Look into my eyes .
Yes , look at me the way Kruvajan did that night
and , like him , lose yourself deep in my eyes .
Don 't you feel the joy and the beauty of hating ?
Look !
She ... She is the witch .
Don 't be deceived by her face . Look at her body .
She is transforming herself into Katia
by draining her life 's blood .
Take her !
Two centuries ago ,
a storm prevented the flames from destroying her wicked soul ,
but today her innocent victims have broken the spell of Satan .
Why ?
Why was Katia taken away from me , Father ?
And she is dying with Katia 's beauty .
Katia ...
My life is finished too now .
How can I ever forget her ?
How can I resign myself ?
I will never find peace .
Look , her young body ... destroyed .
Father !
Katia .